Guide to the Sarita Daftary-Steel collection of East New York oral histories 2015.011
Brooklyn Historical Society
Sarita Daftary-Steel collection of East New York oral histories
2014-2015
Brooklyn Historical Society
Daftary-Steel, Sarita
2015.011
41.3 Gigabytes in 147 files, total running time: 32 hours, 22 minutes, 4 seconds
The collection consists of twenty oral history interviews (with nineteen narrators) conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel with residents (past and present) of the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. The interviews were conducted between January 2014 and February 2015. The project was designed to capture the experiences of East New York residents who lived in the neighborhood during the period when families of color (African American, West Indian, and Puerto Rican) moved in and White families moved out, and the resulting decline of services and quality of life that followed. This process began as early as the 1950s and continued through the rest of the twentieth century. Sarita Daftary-Steel is a community organizer who worked for United Community Centers from 2003 to 2013, most of those years as the East New York Farms! Project Director.
Biographical note
Sarita Daftary-Steel is a community organizer who worked for United Community Centers from 2003 to 2013, most of those years as the East New York Farms! Project Director. As of 2016, she is the Program Director for the El Puente Green Light District and Williamsburg Leadership Center. She attended Georgetown University, where she received a degree in sociology and government, and is also a graduate of the Leadership New York Fellowship, organized by Coro New York and the Leadership Caucus of the Community Resource Exchange.
Source: "Program Directors," El Puente, accessed November 28, 2016, http://elpuente.us/content/program-directors.
Historical note
The East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn was established as part of the Town of Flatbush in 1835 by John Pitkin. It became the independent Town of New Lots in 1852 and was then annexed by the City of Brooklyn in 1886. By the mid-twentieth century, the neighborhood was predominantly Jewish, with some Italian and Irish residents. Starting in the 1950s, African Americans from the Southern United States, as well as Puerto Ricans, began migrating to the neighborhood in search of employment in New York City. As a result of city government policies and real estate interests influencing residents to sell their homes, the neighborhood experienced a rapid demographic change, and most White residents had left by the 1970s. The area then experienced rapid decline in city services, a rise in crime, and an increase of gang and drug activity. Concerned residents formed a number of community organizations to combat the neighborhood's decline. As of 2016, the neighborhood is once again facing the possibility of major demographic changes as the result of gentrification and a lack of affordable housing.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of twenty oral history interviews (with nineteen narrators) conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel with residents (past and present) of the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. The interviews were conducted between January 2014 and February 2015. The project was designed to capture the experiences of East New York residents who lived in the neighborhood during the period when families of color (African American, West Indian, and Puerto Rican) moved in and White families moved out, and the resulting decline of services and quality of life that followed. This process began as early as the 1950s and continued through the rest of the twentieth century. In particular, the narrators discuss race relations, school integration, housing, community organizing, the rise of crime and drug activity, and neighborhood renewal efforts. Public housing, such as the Linden Houses and Starrett City, is frequently discussed. Local schools, especially Thomas Jefferson High School and George Gershwin Junior High School, are referred to throughout the interviews. Several of the narrators (as well as Daftary-Steel) were involved with United Community Centers, a local community activist and integrationist organization, whose activities are also discussed at length. In addition to the interviews, the collection contains digital photographs of some of the narrators.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sarita Daftary-Steel, 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
Oral histories can be accessed onsite at Brooklyn Historical Society's Othmer Library and online on the Oral History Portal.
Oral History note
Oral history interviews are intimate conversations between two people, both of whom have generously agreed to share these recordings with Brooklyn Historical Society archives and with researchers. Please listen in the spirit with which these were shared. Researchers will understand that:
1. Brooklyn Historical Society abides by the General Principles & Best Practices for Oral History as agreed upon by the Oral History Association (2009) and expects that use of this material will be done with respect for these professional ethics.
2. Every oral history relies on the memories, views and opinions of the narrator. Because of the personal nature of oral history, listeners may find some viewpoints or language of the recorded participants to be objectionable. In keeping with its mission of preservation and unfettered access whenever possible, BHS presents these views as recorded.
3. Transcripts created prior to 2008 serve as a guide to the interview and are not considered verbatim. The audio recording should be considered the primary source for each interview. It may contain natural false starts, verbal stumbles, misspeaks, repetitions that are common in conversation, and other passages and phrases omitted from the transcript. This decision was made because BHS gives primacy to the audible voice and also because some researchers do find useful information in these verbal patterns.
4. Unless these verbal patterns are germane to your scholarly work, when quoting from this material researchers are encouraged to correct the grammar and make other modifications maintaining the flavor of the narrator's speech while editing the material for the standards of print.
Related Materials
The following collections also document the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in the mid-to-late 20th century:
N. Jay Jaffee photographs (2014.002)
Harry Kalmus papers and photographs (ARC.046)
Bernard Gotfryd color slides and photographs (V1987.003)
Related Oral Histories note
Brooklyn Historical Society holds the following related oral history collections:
Puerto Rican Oral History Project records (1976.001)
Crossing Borders, Bridging Generations oral history collection (2011.019)
Hispanic Communities Documentation Project records and oral histories (ARC.032)
African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Digital Photographs; Discrimination in housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Oral histories (document genres); Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Puerto Ricans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban policy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Whites |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fairfield Towers (Housing complex); Linden Houses (Housing complex); Nehemiah Housing; New York City Housing Authority; Starrett City (Housing complex); United Community Centers, Inc
- Barksdale, Mary, 2014 March 28; 2015.011.01
  Biographical note
  Mary (Griggs) Barksdale was born in the East Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, New York, in 1931. Her parents were African Americans who had migrated from the southern United States to New York. She lived in the Bronx until the 1960s, when she and her husband bought a house in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. She continues to live in the Starrett City (Spring Creek) section of the neighborhood as of 2014. She was very active in community organizations, such as the United Community Centers and the Council for a Better East New York. She was also a local school board representative and president of the parent-teachers association at her son's school.
  Scope and Contents
  In the interview Mary Barksdale discusses her deep involvement in the issues of education and interracial collaboration in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. She relates how she arrived in East New York in the 1960s, as African American and Hispanic families moved in and White families left. Barksdale speaks in depth on her community activism, especially with United Community Centers. She was heavily involved with improving and integrating the neighborhood's schools. She also discusses her childhood and family, internal conflict at United Community Centers, her hopes for the future, and the worrying trends she sees in our current political climate. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at United Community Centers in East New York.
  African Americans -- Education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Busing for school integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Discrimination in housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Discrimination in mortgage loans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Oral histories (document genres); Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Barksdale, Mary; Council for Better East New York; P.S. 158 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); P.S. 260 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Starrett City (Housing complex); Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Transit Tech High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United Community Centers, Inc
- Bristol, Carlos, 2014 July 29; 2015.011.02
  Carlos Bristol was born in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York, in 1940. His father was born in Brooklyn and was of mixed ancestry (African American and Dutch), and his mother was born in Brooklyn to Barbadian immigrants. As of 2015, he continues to live in East New York in the home his parents purchased in the 1960s. Bristol attended East New York Vocational High School (now Transit Tech Career and Technical Education High School), and then was incarcerated from 1958 to 1971. After his release he returned to East New York, and later earned a bachelor's degree from College of New Rochelle and a master's degree from Hunter College School of Social Work. Bristol has worked in various social service and community development agencies (such as the Fortune Society and Services for the Underserved), is active in community organizations (including the East New York Homeowners Association), and has run for City Council.
  In the interview, Carlos Bristol speaks about the African American enclave he lived in on Cleveland Street in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, his experience in school and involvement with low-level youth gangs, his imprisonment, and his return to East New York in 1971, after which he became heavily involved in community organizing, youth development and mentorship, social services work, and the rebuilding of the neighborhood through the Nehemiah housing program. He recalls many ways that he saw racism affect the community and the development of the young people he grew up with, and about the decline in services that followed the decline in White population. He also talks about his belief that there are plans in place that are likely to bring significant changes to the neighborhood in the future. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Bristol's home in East New York.
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Cleveland Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Low-income housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban policy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bristol, Carlos; East New York Vocational High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); J.H.S. 64 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Nehemiah Housing; P.S. 158 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Transit Tech High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United Community Centers, Inc; Youngblood, Johnny Ray
- Brown, Johanna, 2014 March 16; 2015.011.03
  In the interview, Johanna Brown discusses moving to a predominantly Jewish section of the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, White flight and the decline of services in the area, racism and resistance to integrating public schools, interracial friendships, life at the Linden Houses and Starrett City, United Community Centers, the devastating effect of drugs on the community, the rise of crime and violence (including the murder of a school friend), and the effect of gentrification on the future of the neighborhood. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Brown's home in East New York.
  Approximately twelve minutes of the interview has been removed for privacy reasons.
  Johanna Brown was born in Brooklyn, New York, in 1954. Her father was an African American who was born in Georgia, raised in Philadelphia, and moved to New York after serving in World War II. Her mother was the daughter of African immigrants from Cape Verde. In 1960, her family moved from the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn to Ashford Street in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. The family later moved to the Linden Houses, and finally to the Starrett City (Spring Creek) section of the neighborhood, where she continues to live with her son (as of 2015). She attended PS 108, Bishop McDonnell Memorial High School for Girls, and Thomas Jefferson High School, and now works for the New York City Transit Authority.
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bishop McDonnell Memorial High School for Girls (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brown, Johanna; Linden Houses (Housing complex); P.S. 108 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); P.S. 158 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Starrett City (Housing complex); Thomas Jefferson High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United Community Centers, Inc
- Daniel, Lydia, 2014 July 21; 2015.011.04
  Lydia Daniel was born in Charlotte Amalie, St. Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands, in 1954. She moved to the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan in the late 1950s and later relocated to the Bronx. Her mother moved from the Bronx to the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in the early 1960s, and Daniel followed in the early 1970s. She attended PS 184, James Fenimore Cooper Junior High School, Julia Richman High School, and the Wilfred Academy of Hair and Beauty Culture. She owned and operated a beauty salon in East New York for many years, and her son owns a barber shop (Cas Cuts) in neighborhood. As of 2015, Daniel lives with her daughter in upstate New York.
  In the interview, Lydia Daniel discusses moving to the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, owning her own business and the difficulties she faced securing loans, White flight and the decline of services in the area, integration, gentrification and affordable housing, moving from the US Virgin Islands to New York, and positive aspects of East New York. She also compares her experiences living in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan, the Bronx, and East New York. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Cas Cuts, which is a barbershop owned by her son in East New York.
  African Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |x African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Discrimination in banking |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Entrepreneurship |x African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Low-income housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Daniel, Lydia
- Davidson, Gary, 2014 June 10; 2015.011.05
  In the interview, Gary Davidson describes his family's history in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, the effect the city's policy of planned shrinkage in the 1970s, White flight, changes on his block (Logan Street, between Liberty Avenue and Atlantic Avenue), East Brooklyn Churches and community organizing, the crack cocaine epidemic, police oppression, problems with school integration, and the importance of working together as a community despite racial and ethnic differences. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Davidson's home in East New York.
  Gary Davidson was born in Brooklyn, New York in 1952 to second-generation German immigrant parents and spent the majority of his life in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. He continues to reside in the neighborhood in the house that his great-grandparents purchased in 1907, on Logan Street, between Liberty Avenue and Atlantic Avenue. Davidson attended PS 65 and the High School of Art and Design, and served in the US Navy during the Vietnam War. He is an active member of St. Peter's Lutheran Church and the Green Party.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Logan Street (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real estate business -- New York (State) -- Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban policy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Whites |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Davidson, Gary; East Brooklyn Congregations; Franklin K. Lane High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Nehemiah Housing; St. Peter's Lutheran Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Faulding, Anita, 2014 March 13; 2015.011.06
  In the interview, Anita Faulding discusses living her life in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, especially her experiences with United Community Centers (UCC). She describes how she became involved with UCC as a teenager protesting against school segregation and how she later worked at the organization's integrated day care center. She also discusses living in public housing (Linden Houses and Fairfield Towers), White flight, and eventually leaving East New York for Long Island. Finally, she also speaks on public education, specifically on the effects of segregation and charter schools on students today. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at Faulding's home in Baldwin, New York.
  Anita (Fisher) Faulding was born in the Bronx, New York in 1950 into a Jewish family. Her family moved to the Linden Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1957. She became a member of United Community Centers, a local integrationist organization, as a teenager. Faulding attended PS 213, George Gershwin Junior High School, Thomas Jefferson High School, and Brooklyn College. After graduating college she moved to Fairfield Towers, and then later to Starrett City. She taught pre-school and elementary school in East New York until 2013. Anita married a Black man, Steve Faulding, and they moved with their children to Baldwin, New York (Long Island) in 1991.
  Baldwin (N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Charter schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Day care centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; East New York (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jews |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; School integration |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Whites |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fairfield Towers (Housing complex); Faulding, Anita; Linden Houses (Housing complex); United Community Centers, Inc
- Foglio, Paulette and Holtzman, Jordan, 2014 July 17; 2015.011.07
  Paulette (Giarusso) Foglio was born in Brooklyn in 1953 to Italian parents. Her family was the first to move into the Linden Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn when it opened in 1956, and they lived there until 1969. She attended PS 190, George Gershwin Junior High School, Thomas Jefferson High School, and St. John's University. She is the principal of PS 99 in Kew Gardens, Queens, and currently lives on Long Island, New York.
  In the interview, Paulette Foglio and Jordan Holtzman describe growing up in the Linden Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1950s and 1960s, their experiences in neighborhood schools (especially George Gershwin Junior High School and Thomas Jefferson High School), neighborhood businesses, White flight from the neighborhood and public housing, the rise in crime in the neighborhood, integration and race relations, and their feelings about the neighborhood today. The interview was conducted by Sarita Daftary-Steel at PS 99 in Kew Gardens, Queens, New York.
  Jordan Holtzman was born in Brooklyn in 1946 to Jewish parents. His family moved to the Linden Houses in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1950s, where they remained until the 1970s. He attended PS 190, George Gershwin Junior High School, Thomas Jefferson High School, New York City Community College, and Baruch College. He served in the U.S. Army during the Vietnam War. He worked as a stock trader on Wall Street for 25 years, and now works as a Parent Coordinator at PS 99 in Kew Gardens, Queens, New York. He lives in Forest Hills, Queens, New York.